In 2011, during the final six months of Kim Jong-Il's life,
في عام 2011- اخر 6 اشهر في حياة القائد كيم جونج إل-
I lived undercover in North Korea.
عشت متخفية في كوريا الشمالية.
I was born and raised in South Korea, their enemy.
لقد ولدت و ترعرت في كوريا الجنوبية -عدوهم-.
I live in America, their other enemy.
وعشت في امريكا -عدوهم الاخر-.
Since 2002, I had visited North Korea a few times.
منذ عام 2002، كنت قد زرت كوريا الشمالية عدة مرات .
And I had come to realize that to write about it with any meaning,
و قد ادركت ان عليّ للكتابة عن كوريا الشمالية
or to understand the place beyond the regime's propaganda,
او لفهم هذا المكان بعيدا عن دعاية النظام،
the only option was total immersion.
فان خياري الوحيد هو الانغماس فيه.
So I posed as a teacher and a missionary
ولذلك تظاهرت انني معلمة و مبشرة
at an all-male university in Pyongyang.
في جامعة للشباب فقط في العاصمة بيونغ يانغ.
The Pyongyang University of Science and Technology
جامعة بيونغ يانغ للعلوم والتكنولوجيا
was founded by Evangelical Christians who cooperate with the regime
أسسها المسيحيون الانجيليون الذين تعاونوا مع النظام
to educate the sons of the North Korean elite,
لتعليم ابناء نخبة كوريا الشمالية ،
without proselytizing, which is a capital crime there.
من دون التبشير -التي تعد جريمة كبيرة هناك-.
The students were 270 young men, expected to be the future leaders
كان الطلاب 270 شاباّ فتياً الذين يعدّون قادة مستقبل
of the most isolated and brutal dictatorship in existence.
اكثر الاماكن الديكتاتورية وحشية و عزلة في الوجود.
When I arrived, they became my students.
عندنا وصلت ،أصبحوا تلاميذي.
2011 was a special year,
2011 كانت سنة مميزة،
marking the 100th anniversary of the birth of North Korea's original Great Leader,
التي تصادف الذكرى 100 لميلاد القائد العظيم الاول ،
Kim Il-Sung.
كيم إل سونغ.
To celebrate the occasion, the regime shut down all universities,
للاحتفال في هذه المناسبة قام النظام بتعليق دوام كل الجامعات
and sent students off to the fields
و ارسال الطلاب الى الحقول
to build the DPRK's much-heralded ideal
لتعزيز مفهوم كوريا الشمالية
as the world's most powerful and prosperous nation.
بانها اكثر دول العالم قوة و ازدهارا.
My students were the only ones spared from that fate.
كان تلامذتي المستثنين الوحيدين من هذا الامر.
North Korea is a gulag posing as a nation.
كوريا الشمالية هي عبارة عن معسكرات عمل تتظاهر بانها دولة.
Everything there is about the Great Leader.
كل شي هناك يدور حول القائد العظيم .
Every book, every newspaper article, every song, every TV program --
كل كتاب،وكل مقالة في الجريدة ، كل اغنية ، و كل برنامج تلفازي..
there is just one subject.
هناك موضوع واحد فقط .
The flowers are named after him,
حتى الازهار قد سميت باسمه ،
the mountains are carved with his slogans.
و تم نحت شعاراته على الجبال.
Every citizen wears the badge of the Great Leader at all times.
ويرتدي كل مواطن شارة تحمل صورته في جميع الاوقات.
Even their calendar system begins with the birth of Kim Il-Sung.
حتى نظام التقويم لديهم يبدأ بميلاد كيم إل سونغ.
The school was a heavily guarded prison, posing as a campus.
كانت الجامعة مشددة الحراسة كالسجن تظهر كانها حرم جامعة.
Teachers could only leave on group outings accompanied by an official minder.
وكان للمعلمين الخروج كمجموعات فقط ويكون برفقتهم مراقب رسمي .
Even then, our trips were limited to sanctioned national monuments
ومع هذا كانت رحلاتنا محددة فقط بزيارة معالم اثرية وطنية
celebrating the Great Leader.
للاحتفال بالقائد العظيم.
The students were not allowed to leave the campus,
لم يكن مسموحا للطلاب مغادرة حرم الجامعة
or communicate with their parents.
او التواصل مع اهاليهم.
Their days were meticulously mapped out, and any free time they had
وكانت ايامهم مخططة بشكل دقيق وان كان لديهم اوقات فراغ
was devoted to honoring their Great Leader.
كانت مكرسة لإجلال واحترام قائدهم العظيم.
Lesson plans had to meet the approval of North Korean staff,
كان يجب ان يوافق العاملون الكوريون الشماليون على خطط الدرس ،
every class was recorded and reported on, every room was bugged,
كل حصة كانت تسجل و يرسل بها تقرير ، وكان يتم التنصت على كل غرفة،
and every conversation, overheard.
وكان يتم التسمع على كل المحادثات.
Every blank space was covered with the portraits of Kim Il-Sung and Kim Jong-Il,
وكل جهة فارغة كان يتم تغطيتها بصور كيم ال سونغ و كيم جونغ ال،
like everywhere else in North Korea.
ككل مكان في كوريا الشمالية.
We were never allowed to discuss the outside world.
لم يكن مسموحا لنا ابدا مناقشة العالم الخارجي.
As students of science and technology, many of them were computer majors
باعتبارهم طلاب في العلوم و التكنولوجيا كان العديد منهم متخصصون في الكمبيوتر
but they did not know the existence of the Internet.
لكنهم كانوا يجهلون وجود الانترنت.
They had never heard of Mark Zuckerberg or Steve Jobs.
لم يسمعوا قط بمارك زوكربيرج او ستيف جوبز.
Facebook, Twitter -- none of those things would have meant a thing.
الفيسبوك او التويتر..لم تعني لهم شيئا.
And I could not tell them.
وانا لم استطع اخبارهم.
I went there looking for truth.
لقد ذهبت هناك للعثور على الحقيقة.
But where do you even start when an entire nation's ideology,
لكن اين ستبدأ عندما نكون ايدولوجية دولة كاملة ،
my students' day-to-day realities,
والوقائع اليومية لطلابي،
and even my own position at the universities,
وحتى منصبي في الجامعات،
were all built on lies?
مبنيّ كله على الكذبات ؟
I started with a game.
بدأت كل شي بلعبة.
We played "Truth and Lie."
لعبنا لعبة "الحقيقة و الكذبة".
A volunteer would write a sentence on the chalkboard,
يكتب متطوع على اللوح جملة،
and the other students had to guess
وعلى بقية الطلاب أن يحزروا
whether it was a truth or a lie.
إن كانت حقيقة او كذبة.
Once a student wrote, "I visited China last year on vacation,"
في مرة كتب طالب "لقد زرت الصين للسياحة العام الماضي" ،
and everyone shouted, "Lie!"
و حينها صاح الجميع ، "كذبة!"
They all knew this wasn't possible.
كلهم يعلمون ان هذا غير معقول.
Virtually no North Korean is allowed to leave the country.
فعليا لا يسمح لاحد من الكوريون الشماليون مغادرة البلاد .
Even traveling within their own country requires a travel pass.
حتى السفر داخل بلدهم يحتاج تأشيرة عبور.
I had hoped that this game would reveal some truth about my students,
ولقد تأملت ان تكشف هذه اللعبة بعض الحقائق عن طلابي ،
because they lie so often and so easily,
لانهم يكذبون اغلب الوقت و بكل بساطة.
whether about the mythical accomplishments of their Great Leader,
سواء كان عن انجازات قائدهم العظيم الاسطورية ،
or the strange claim that they cloned a rabbit as fifth graders.
او الادعاء الغريب باستنساخهم أرنبا عندما كانوا في الصف الخامس.
The difference between truth and lies seemed at times hazy to them.
كان الفرق بين الحقيقة و الكذبة يبدو مبهما لهم .
It took me a while to understand the different types of lies;
لقد استغرقت بعض الوقت لأفهم الانواع المختلفة من الكذبات :
they lie to shield their system from the world,
يكذبون لحماية نظامهم من العالم ،
or they were taught lies, and were just regurgitating them.
او قيلت لهم الكذبات و هم كانوا فقط يرددونها دون وعي .
Or, at moments, they lied out of habit.
او - للحظات- كانوا يكذبون لانهم اعتادوا الكذب.
But if all they have ever known were lies,
لكن بما ان كل ما عرفوه يوما كان كذبات ،
how could we expect them to be otherwise?
كيف لنا ان نتوقع منهم ان يكونوا غير ذلك ؟
Next, I tried to teach them essay writing.
وبعدها حاولت تعليمهم كتابة المقالات.
But that turned out to be nearly impossible.
ولكن هذا كله اتضح انه مستحيل.
Essays are about coming up with one's own thesis,
ان كتابة المقال تستلزم كتابة فرضيات واطروحات الفرد الشخصية،
and making an evidence-based argument to prove it.
ثم القيام بتجارب قائمة على الدلائل لاثبات تلك الفرضيات.
These students, however, were simply told what to think,
لكن هؤلاء الطلبة قد قيل لهم سلفا بماذا و كيف يفكرون
and they obeyed.
و هم اطاعوا .
In their world, critical thinking was not allowed.
كان التفكير النقدي في عالمهم غير مسموح به.
I also gave them the weekly assignment of writing a personal letter,
و لقد طلبت منهم كواجب اسبوعي ان يكتبوا رسالة شخصية
to anybody.
لاي احد.
It took a long time, but eventually some of them began to write
وهذا استغرق وقتا طويلا الى ان بدأ بعضهم بالكتابة
to their mothers, their friends, their girlfriends.
الى امهاتهم ، اصدقائهم ،و حبيباتهم.
Although those were just homework,
على الرغم من ان هذه الرسائل كانت عبارة عن واجب ،و
and would never reach their intended recipients,
لن تصل ابدا الى مستلميها المقصودين.
my students slowly began to reveal their true feelings in them.
شيئا فشيئا بدأ طلابي بالافصاح عن مشاعرهم الداخلية الحقيقة .
They wrote that they were fed up with the sameness of everything.
كتبوا انهم ضاقوا ذرعا بتشابه كل شي حولهم.
They were worried about their future.
انهم قلقون من مستقبلهم .
In those letters, they rarely ever mentioned their Great Leader.
في هذه الرسائل قلما ذكروا قائدهم العظيم.
I was spending all of my time with these young men.
لقد قضيت كل وقتي مع هؤلاء الشباب الفتيين .
We all ate meals together, played basketball together.
لقد كنا نأكل معا، ونلعب كرة السلة معا.
I often called them gentlemen, which made them giggle.
وكنت اناديهم عادة بالرجال النبلاء مما جعلهم يقهقهون .
They blushed at the mention of girls.
وكانوا يحمرون خجلا عند ذكر الفتيات.
And I came to adore them.
وانا مع الوقت احببتهم.
And watching them open up even in the tiniest of ways,
و كانت رؤيتهم ينفتحون حتى قليلا ،
was deeply moving.
كان مؤثرا حقا.
But something also felt wrong.
لكن شعرت ان هناك خطأ ما .
During those months of living in their world,
في تلك الشهور التي قضيتها في عالمهم ،
I often wondered if the truth would, in fact, improve their lives.
تسالت اذا ما كانت الحقيقة فعلا ستجعل حياتهم افضل.
I wanted so much to tell them the truth,
لقد اردت و بشدة اخبارهم الحقيقة،
of their country and of the outside world,
عن بلدهم و العالم الخارجي،
where Arab youth were turning their rotten regime inside out,
حيث كان الشباب العربي يقلبون انظمة بلادهم العفنة راسا على عقب،
using the power of social media,
باستخدام وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي،
where everyone except them was connected through the world wide web,
حيث كان الجميع مرتبطا باستثنائهم بالشبكة العنكبوتية العالمية
which wasn't worldwide after all.
التي يبدوا انها ليست عالمية .
But for them, the truth was dangerous.
لكن بالنسبة لهم ، كانت الحقيقة خطرة.
By encouraging them to run after it, I was putting them at risk --
كنت بتشجيعهم لملاحقة الحقيقة اعرضهم للخطر
of persecution,
خطر الاضطهاد،
of heartbreak.
خطر تحطم قلوبهم.
When you're not allowed to express anything in the open,
عندما لا يكون الافصاح مسموحا به ،
you become good at reading what is unspoken.
تصبح بارعا في قراءة ما لا يقال.
In one of their personal letters to me, a student wrote that he understood
في احد رسائلهم الي ، كتب طالب انه يعرف
why I always called them gentlemen.
لماذا اناديهم بالرجال النبلاء.
It was because I was wishing them to be gentle in life, he said.
لانني اتمنى ان يكونوا نبلاء في الحياة ،هكذا قال.
On my last day in December of 2011,
في يومي الاخير في شهر ديسمبر 2011،
the day Kim Jong-Il's death was announced,
يوم اعلان وفاة كيم جونغ إل ،
their world shattered.
تحطم عالمهم.
I had to leave without a proper goodbye.
كان علي المغادرة دون توديعهم وداعا مناسبا .
But I think they knew how sad I was for them.
لكنني اظن انهم يعلمون كم كنت حزينة عليهم .
Once, toward the end of my stay, a student said to me,
في احد المرات -في اخر فترة خدمتي- قال لي احد الطلاب :
"Professor, we never think of you as being different from us.
"بروفسورة، لا نظن ابدا انك مختلفة عنا .
Our circumstances are different, but you're the same as us.
ظروفنا مختلفة لكننا متشابهون.
We want you to know that we truly think of you as being the same."
نريدك ان تعلمي اننا فعلا نراك مشابهة لنا" .
Today, if I could respond to my students with a letter of my own,
اليوم ان امكنني الرد على طلابي برسالة مني لهم ،
which is of course impossible,
وهو طبعا مستحيل،
I would tell them this:
كنت لاقول لهم هذا :
"My dear gentlemen,
" اعزائي الرجال النبلاء،
It's been a bit over three years since I last saw you.
مرت اكثر من 3 سنوات منذ اخر مرة رايتكم فيها .
And now, you must be 22 -- maybe even as old as 23.
والان قد تكونون في 22 او ربما اكبر قليلا في 23 من عمركم .
At our final class, I asked you if there was anything you wanted.
في درسنا الاخير سألتكم ان كان هناك شيئا تريدونه.
The only wish you expressed, the only thing you ever asked of me
امنيتكم الوحيدة التي اعربتم عنها و الشي الوحيد الذي طلبتموه مني
in all those months we spent together,
في كل تلك الاشهر التي قضيناها معا
was for me to speak to you in Korean.
كانت ان اتحدث معكم باللغة الكورية.
Just once.
مرة واحدة فقط.
I was there to teach you English;
كنت هناك لادرسكم الانجليزية
you knew it wasn't allowed.
وكنتم تعلمون ان هذا غير مسموح.
But I understood then, you wanted to share that bond of our mother tongue.
ولكنني علمت حينها انكم اردتم ان نتشارك رابطة الحديث بلغتنا الام.
I called you my gentlemen,
لقد كنت اناديكم رجالي النبلاء،
but I don't know if being gentle in Kim Jong-Un's merciless North Korea
لكنني لا اعلم ان كان النبل في حكم كيم جونغ ون القاسي لكوريا الشمالية
is a good thing.
امرا جيدا.
I don't want you to lead a revolution --
لا اريدكم ان تقودوا ثورة
let some other young person do it.
فلتدعوا شبابا اخرين يقودوها.
The rest of the world might casually encourage or even expect
بقية العالم قد تشجع او تتوقع
some sort of North Korean Spring,
ربيعا كوريا شماليا ،
but I don't want you to do anything risky,
لكنني لا اريدكم ان تقوموا باي عمل يعرضكم للخطر
because I know in your world, someone is always watching.
لانني اعلم ان في عالمكم هناك دائما من يراقب.
I don't want to imagine what might happen to you.
لا اريد حتى تخيل ما قد يصيبكم حينها .
If my attempts to reach you have inspired something new in you,
اذا كانت محاولاتي في الوصول اليكم قد ألهمت شئيا جديدا فيكم
I would rather you forget me.
أفضل أن تنسوني على ذلك.
Become soldiers of your Great Leader, and live long, safe lives.
كونوا جنودا لقائدكم العظيم و عيشوا طويلا وعيشوا بامان.
You once asked me if I thought your city of Pyongyang was beautiful,
في احد المرات سالتموني ان كنت اظن عاصمتكم بيونغ يانغ جميلة ،
and I could not answer truthfully then.
لم استطع ان اجاوب بصدق حينها.
But I know why you asked.
لكنني أعلم لماذا سألتم .
I know that it was important for you to hear that I, your teacher,
اعلم انه كان مهما بالنسبة لكم ان تسمعوا مني ،انا معلمتكم
the one who has seen the world that you are forbidden from,
-التي رات العالم المحرم عليكم -
declare your city as the most beautiful.
أقرّ ان عاصمتكم هي اجمل المدن.
I know hearing that would make your lives there a bit more bearable,
اعلم ان سماعكم ذلك كان ليجعلكم تتحملون حياتكم اكثر قليلا،
but no, I don't find your capital beautiful.
لكن لا ، انا لا اجد عاصمتكم جميلة.
Not because it's monotone and concrete,
ليس لانها جامدة و رتيبة ،
but because of what it symbolizes:
لكن بسبب ما تمثل :
a monster that feeds off the rest of the country,
وحش يقتات على باقي الدولة
where citizens are soldiers and slaves.
حيث ان مواطنيها عبارة عن جنود و عبيد.
All I see there is darkness.
الظلام هو كل ما اراه فيها .
But it's your home, so I cannot hate it.
لكنها موطنكم ولذلك لا استطيع كرهها.
And I hope instead that you, my lovely young gentlemen,
وانني اتمنى -بدلا من ذلك- ان تقوموا يا رجالي النبلاء المحبوبين الفتيين
will one day help make it beautiful.
بجعلها مكانا اجمل .
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)